by the time you are in your 40s you know
where do you stand in your financial
journey in continuation of our last
video on financial planning for your 20s
and 30s let's see how you can plan for
your 40s
[Music]
if you are in your 20s and 30s use this
video as an example on what problems you
can avoid if you are careful with your
money right now
if you are in your 40s you may be on the
positive side knowing that you have
taken just the right steps money-wise
you have invested the right amount in
your 20s and 30s and a good retirement
is well within your reach or
you may not be so happy and struggling
with how to secure a nest egg that will
last all your retirement in your 20s you
can take a lot of risks there would be a
lot many roads that can take you to your
goal of financial freedom but as you
reach 40s and 50s your options begin to
slim down you can still reach your goal
of financial freedom it's still very
much doable
it's just that you need to be a little
bit more disciplined now in our previous
videos we are looking at how much you
need to invest
if you are in your 20s and 30s to hit
the one crore and the 10 crore mark by
the time you turn 60
if you are in your 40s and struggling
you may choose to work for five extra
years and retire at 65. your financial
freedom is not a lost cause it's just
that you need a little bit more time on
your side don't move the goal post
in your 40s as you reach a certain level
of seniority in your organization you
become a vp or a director you may feel
that you need to drive a certain brand
of car that suits your station you may
want to live in a certain part of your
city this is not just a lifestyle creep
that you face when you start living
comfortably a bit of this may be from
the peer pressure but mostly it comes
from within can you call it mid-life
crisis see if you wanted to buy a
certain car or a certain type of home in
your 20s and 30s and if you have that
now hold on to it you do not need to
upgrade immediately if you have the
model x of your favorite car you do not
need to buy the newer model y
immediately
do not move the goal post if you are
already struggling and you keep jumping
from one shining object to the next you
will never reach your goal of financial
freedom how about your health
in your 40s if you're not taking care of
your health you're going to spend a bomb
on hospital bills in your 50s and 60s
and i'm saying this as a financial
advice not as your doctor
you know the cost of medical procedures
in india angioplasty starts at two and a
half lakh dialysis is thirty thousand a
month insulin can cost around twelve
thousand rupees every month forties is
probably your last easy stop where you
can take precautionary care of your
health because if you are not careful
things can go downhill very easily
you can let a financial planner manage
your finances but for your health you
need to work out yourself right and you
need to actively decide that you are not
going to take your health for granted
insurance
if you have not taken health insurance
already this is kind of a last chance to
buy health insurance at a fair price
while you are still reasonably healthy
you will see that if you buy now you
would have to pay a higher premium
compared to what you would have paid if
you have got the insurance in your 30s
but it is still better to buy now
than wait and buy in your 50s when the
premiums will go so high
that it will feel like an extortion in
your 20s and 30s buying insurance is
mostly about emergency care what if i
got in an accident in your 40s you also
need to think about long-term care if
you feel that your coverage is low you
can add floater cover to your primary
health policy
floater policies are a top-up on your
existing health policy that increases
your overall coverage do a basic check
of your retirement planning there are
many calculators available online that
you can use for this purpose these
calculators mostly use the four percent
withdrawal rate and
all these calculators will give slightly
different numbers based on their
parameters
but you only need four basic numbers to
work with these calculators number one
the amount you have already saved up for
your retirement number two the amount
you can save from now till your
retirement every month number three your
estimated expense at the time of
retirement and number four
the amount of return that you can
reasonably expect to generate for the
four percent withdrawal rule you simply
multiply your annual expenses by 25
this is the amount of corpus you need at
the time of your retirement and you can
safely withdraw four percent from it
every year
if you want to play a bit more
conservatively you can multiply your
annual expenses by 33 to gauge your
retirement corpus
this is just an estimated number but if
you feel that you are lagging behind on
these numbers you need to be ruthless
with your budget you know time is not as
much on your side as it was 10 years ago
but this is still not all doomed
your 100 rupees at 40 can still turn
into 1083 rupees by the time you are 65
all you need to do is be really
conscious of where your money is going
services of a financial planner
if you have doubts on your numbers and
you are not sure where do you stand and
if you will be able to make it to a
comfortable retirement engage the
services of a financial planner they
will help you understand whether you are
on track and help you make the needed
adjustment you will be able to course
correct while there is still time on
your side in the earlier videos we did a
section on bonus tips that could help
you in the long term we talked about
filing your tax returns and updating
your nominee details in your bank
account investment account and insurance
today i have a recommendation for you
not a tip if you are doing good
financially 40s is a great time to
consider giving back
well you can also start in your 20s and
30s there is actually no age limit for
this
choose a cause that moves you
educating a girl child or feeding poor
families or supporting old age homes
whatever moves you and contribute with
your time or money or both
okay let's get to the numbers now
in our last video we have seen that you
only need to invest 3500 or 6300 every
month at the rate of 10 return
to hit the one crore mark by the time
you turn 60 if you start at 31 or 36
years of age respectively
now when you are in your 40s this number
jumps up a little bit but still doable
you can hit the one curve mark by the
time you turn 65
if you only invest 8 000 or 14 000 every
month
starting at 41 or 46 years of age
respectively to hit the 10 curve mark
you need to put in 80 000 or one lakh 40
000 every month if you start at 41 or 46
years of age respectively if you are in
your 40s and you feel you are lagging
behind this is not the time to take
undue risk be pragmatic aim for a
reasonable rate of return and try to
increase the amount you are investing as
much as possible if you do not even have
a plan for your retirement it's
imperative that you start saving
immediately for your golden years and
plan your finances accordingly it's time
to sit down and chalk out the road ahead
to ensure a stress-free retirement and a
prosperous time in your golden years may
this video give you hope that all is not
lost there is still time may your 50s be
a time of celebration and not panic hit
the like button click subscribe and
press the bell icon wrapping up this
peritosh signing off